Peck Family Papers, 1815-1920, undated
Elmira College
Peck Family Papers, 1815-1920, undated
The Peck Family Papers are primarily comprised of correspondence and photographs. The bulk of the letters are correspondence between Mary Gray Peck and her mother, Mary Diantha Gray Peck as well as letters from her father, Henry Jones Peck. The bulk of Mary Gray Peck’s letters were written while a student and depict the academic rigor and social life at Elmira Female College in Elmira, N.Y. and are followed by letters from her time in New York City and Minnesota, while teaching and studying at the University of Minnesota. Letters from Mary’s two brothers, James and Fred, including her sister-in-laws, are also represented in the collection. A number of the photographs were taken on the family farm in Phelps, N.Y. All members of the immediate family of Henry and Mary Diantha are in the collection, including a number of professional photographs of Mary Gray Peck and her friend and fellow suffragist, Frances Squire Potter. The papers document the history of a well-educated family from upstate New York in the late 19th Century and early 20th Century. Letters concerning the professional activities of the Peck children, including Mary Gray Peck’s involvement in the suffrage movement, though present, are at a minimum.
1.67 Linear ft.
Peck
Elmira College
Unrestricted
Henry J. Peck, born in 1834, was adopted by his uncle, Henry W. Jones, after the death of his mother, Juliette Jones. He attended Oberlin College studying music, history, religion and surveying. He returned home to Phelps, N.Y. in 1858 after graduation to help run the family farm, marrying Mary Diantha Gray in 1859.
Mary Diantha was a member of the first class of the Elmira Female College in 1855.
Henry and Mary Diantha had three children: Frederick Burritt, James Ingraham, and Mary Gray Peck. Frederick was born in 1860 and became a professor of geology and mineralogy at Lafayette College in Easton, PA after receiving a Ph.D from the University of Munich in 1896. He married Mary Gray Peck’s college friend, Cora Horton in 1900. He died after several years of poor health in 1925.
James, born in 1863, received a Ph.D from Williams College. He taught Biology at his alma mater and joined the U.S. Fish Commission, studying the water supply of Boston. He was the assistant director of Marine Biology at Woods Hole, MA. In 1890, he married Marion Hitchcock. He died at the age of 35 of pneumonia, Nov. 4, 1898.
Mary Gray Peck, born October 21, 1867 spent her formative years, 1884 to 1889, at Elmira Female College. After graduation, she studied music in New York City, eventually moving to Minnesota to teaching English at the University of Minnesota. She left the University while working on her Ph.D to join, friend and fellow suffragist, Frances Squire Potter, in the ranks of the growing Suffrage Movement in the United States and abroad. Peck would hold several jobs, first as a secretary for the National American Woman Suffrage Association, and later, as the secretary and biographer of leading suffragist, Carrie Chapman Catt.
[Information compiled from: Letters Home by Patricia Parr, The Eagle, Fall 2002, Vol. 1, No. 2.]
Peck, Mary Gray; Peck, Mary Diantha Gray, 1838-1910; Peck, Henry Jones, 1834-1924; Potter, Frances Squire, 1867-1914; Peck, James Ingraham, 1863-1898; Peck, Frederick Burritt, 1860-1925; Peck, Cora; Peck, Marion; Elmira Female College; Elmira (N.Y.)—History—19th Century; Seneca Castle (N.Y.)—History—19th Century; Elmira College—History—19th Century; Suffragists; Letters; Photographs; Diaries
The bulk of the Mary Gray Peck Family Papers are correspondence between Mary Gray Peck and her mother, Mary Diantha Gray Peck as well as letters from Mary’s father, Henry Jones Peck. Mary Gray Peck’s letters were primarily written while a student and depict the academic rigor and social life of the Elmira Female College and are followed by letters from her time in New York City and Minnesota, while teaching and studying at the University of Minnesota. The letters from the later period often mention her growing friendship with Frances Squire Potter with whom she would leave the University in 1909 to actively participate in the growing international suffrage movement.
Letters from Mary’s two brothers, James and Fred, including her sister-in-laws, are also represented in the collection as well as numerous letters written to Mary Gray Peck from her nieces and nephews.
A number of the photographs were taken on the family property in Phelps, N.Y. with all members of the immediate family of Henry and Mary Diantha present. Professional photographs of Mary Gray Peck and friend and fellow suffragist, Frances Squire Potter, are highlights of the photograph collection
The collection contains several miscellaneous family documents, including Mary Gray Peck’s International Women’s Suffrage Alliance booklets as well as family legal documents, including Henry Jones Peck’s Soldier Power of Attorney form from the civil war.
ORGANIZATIONAL NOTE:
The Mary Gray Peck Family Papers are organized into the following series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1852-1917, undated
Sub-Series 1: Mary Gray Peck and Family Correspondence, 1884-1917, undated
Sub-Series 2: Family Correspondence, 1852-1917, undated
Series 2: Photographs, undated
Series 3: Miscellaneous Materials, 1815-1920
Series 4: Peck Family Research Materials, 2002
- SERIES 1: CORRESPONDENCE, 1884 - 1917
  - SUB-SERIES 1: MARY GRAY PECK AND FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, 1884-1917, undated, SUB-SERIES NOTE: This sub-series is comprised of correspondence primarily between Mary Gray Peck and her parents, Mary Diantha and Henry Jones Peck. Letters from Mary Gray Peck’s brothers, sisters-in-law, and nieces are also included. This sub-series is organized chronologically.
    - 1884 Correspondence -- Family letters primarily about daily life, Mary writes about her first term at Elmira College [1884] (Box-folder 1 1)
    - 1885 Correspondence -- Family letters, primarily about daily life, Mary writes about her experiences at Elmira College [1885] (Box-folder 1 2)
    - 1886 Correspondence -- Primarily correspondence between Mary and her mother, Mary writes of her experiences at Elmira College, including writing for Sibyl, a college publication [1886] (Box-folder 1 3)
    - 1887 Correspondence -- Mary's correspondence with her parents, Mary writes of her experiences at Elmira College [1887] (Box-folder 1 4)
    - 1888 Correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her mother, primarily concerning daily life and Mary's activities at the College [1888] (Box-folder 1 5)
    - 1889 Correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her mother, primarily concerning daily life and life at Elmira College; there is no mention of Mary's graduation from Elmira College [1889] (Box-folder 1 6)
    - 1892 Letter -- A letter from Mother to Mary, primarily writing about daily activities and chores [1890] (Box-folder 1 7)
    - 1893 Correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her parents, Mary writes from Brooklyn (Box-folder 1 8)
    - 1894 Correspondence – Correspondence primarily between Mary and her mother, Mary continues to write from Brooklyn (Box-folder 1 9)
    - 1895 -- Correspondence between Mary and her mother, Mary writes from Garwood, N.J. and Brooklyn, N.Y. (Box-folder 1 10)
    - 1897-1898 Correspondence -- Family correspondence [1897-1898] (Box-folder 1 11)
    - 1899 Correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her parents, Mary writes from Minneapolis [1899] (Box-folder 1 12)
    - 1900-1902 Correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her parents; Mary writes of the possibility of attaining a position in the University of Minnesota; Frances Squire Potter is mentioned several times [1900-1902] (Box-folder 1 12)
    - 1903-1904 Correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her parents; descriptions of daily life [1903-1904] (Box-folder 1 13)
    - 1905 Correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her mother, father and brother, Fred; letter mentioning Mary's studies in Cambridge [1905] (Box-folder 1 14)
    - 1906 Correspondence - Letters to Mary from various members of the family [1906] (Box-folder 1 15)
    - 1907 Correspondence -- Letters to Mary from her family [1907] (Box-folder 2 1)
    - 1908 Correspondence -- Letters to Mary from her family; letter from Nov. 11th from her father, suggests Mary's involvement in the political landscape, perhaps her work with the suffrage movement [1908] (Box-folder 2 2)
    - 1909 Correspondence -- Letters to Mary from her parents, includes letter from Henry upset at Mary’s involvement in suffrage movement [1909] (Box-folder 2 3)
    - 1910 Correspondence -- Letters to Mary from her parents; letters from her father concerning the health of her mother [1910] (Box-folder 2 4)
    - 1912-1917 Correspondence -- Primarily letters from Mary's father, in June 20th letter, he acknowledges securing the right of women to vote in Illinois [1912-1917, undated] (Box-folder 2 5)
    - undated correspondence – Correspondence between Mary and her parents [undated], 1815-1920 (Box-folder 2 6)
  - SUB-SERIES 2: FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, 1852-1917, undated, SUB-SERIES NOTE: The letters in Family Correspondence are primarily letters between Fred and James and their parents. There are no letters to or from Mary Gray Peck in this sub-series.
    - James and Marian Peck -- Family Correspondence [1881-1899, undated] (Box-folder 2 7)
    - Fred and Cora Peck -- Family Correspondence [1875-1891] (Box-folder 2 8)
    - Fred and Cora Peck -- Family Correspondence [1896-1909, undated] (Box-folder 2 9)
    - Miscellaneous Family letters (does not include Mary Gray Peck) [1852-1917, undated] (Box-folder 2 10)
- SERIES 2: PHOTOGRAPHS, undated, SERIES 3: MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS, 1815-1920 This series contains materials owned by the Gray-Peck family. These materials are arranged chronologically with a folder of assorted documents at the end of the series.
  - Mary Gray Peck [undated] (Box-folder 3 1)
  - Frances Squire Potter [undated] (Box-folder 3 2)
  - Peck Family Photograph Album [undated] (Box-folder 3 3)
  - Peck Family Photographs (1) [undated] (Box-folder 3 4)
  - Peck Family Photographs (2) [undated] (Box-folder 3 5)
  - Peck Family Photographs (3) [undated] (Box-folder 3 6)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (1) [undated] (Box-folder 3 7)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (2) [undated] (Box-folder 3 8)
- SERIES 3: MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS, 1815-1920, SERIES 3: MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS, 1815-1920 This series contains materials owned by the Gray-Peck family. These materials are arranged chronologically with a folder of assorted documents at the end of the series.
  - Mary Nash Arnett Gray Diaries -- Wife of B.B. Gray, diaries for years 1867 and 1880 [1867, 1880] (Box-folder 4 1)
  - James D. Peck -- Obituaries [1898] (Box-folder 4 2)
  - The International Woman Suffrage Alliance: 6th Congress [1911] (Box-folder 4 3)
  - Patience: An Alliterative version of Jonah by the Poet of Pearl, edited by Professor Gollancz [1913] (Box-folder 4 4)
  - The International Woman Suffrage Alliance: 8th Congress [1920] (Box-folder 4 5)
  - Miscellaneous Documents -- Including Indentures, clippings, Soldier's Power of Attorney for Henry J. Peck, Pre-academic Certificate for William Burritt [1815-1913] (Box-folder 4 6)